Donald Barthelme Forum Collection, 1956-1960
University of Houston Libraries
Donald Barthelme Forum Collection
1956-1960
Barthelme, Donald
3 boxes; 1 ft. 6 in.
1969-004
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Writer Donald Barthelme founded the journal Forum in 1956 while working at the University of Houston, and served as editor until 1960. This quarterly journal featured articles on a wide range of topics including philosophy, literary criticism, economics, anthropology, psychology, biology, mathematics, architecture, film, music, and theater. The collection contains three manuscript boxes of materials related to Barthelme's tenure as editor of Forum.
Biographical Note
Donald Barthelme, short story writer, novelist, editor, journalist, and teacher, was born in Philadelphia on April 7, 1931. In 1933, his family moved to Houston, Texas where his father, Donald Barthelme, Sr., soon established himself as a well-known architect in the style of Mies and Corbusier. Barthelme got an early start in journalism at St. Thomas and Lamar High Schools in Houston.
In the fall of 1949, he enrolled at the University of Houston where he worked on the staff of the Daily Cougar and, as a 20-year-old sophomore journalism major, was the youngest student in the Cougar's history to hold the position of editor. Before graduating, he was drafted into the Army in February of 1953, served in Korea and worked on an Army newspaper there. When he returned to Houston in late 1954, he began working as a reporter for the Houston Post. In September of 1955, he began working for Farris Block at the University of Houston News Service, writing speeches for the President of the University, and, the next year, he succeeded Block as editor of Acta Diurna, a weekly newsletter for University of Houston faculty and staff.
The University of Houston published the first issue of Forum in September 1956. Founded by Barthelme and edited by him until 1960, this quarterly journal featured articles on a wide range of topics including philosophy, literary criticism, economics, anthropology, psychology, biology, mathematics, architecture, film, music, and theater. In 1961, Barthelme became director of the Contemporary Arts Museum in Houston but resigned the following year to move to New York and pursue his career as a writer.
Once in New York, he began to publish frequently in the New Yorker where Roger Angell became his editor and mentor. As a writer, Barthelme has been characterized as an avant-garde or postmodern stylist who relies more on language than plot or character. Upon arriving in New York, he also served as editor of Harold Rosenberg and Thomas Hess's art and literature journal, Location, for the publication's short life of two issues. He lived in New York for 18 years, occasionally teaching at the City University of New York, and then, in 1980, moved back to Houston to serve as the Director of the Creative Writing Program at the University of Houston. Barthelme died of throat cancer in 1989 at the age of 58.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains three manuscript boxes of materials related to Barthelme's tenure as editor of Forum. Researchers may be interested in the Forum collection of materials post-dating Barthelme's time as editor.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects (Persons)
Barthelme, Donald
Subjects
Forum (Houston, Tex)
Formats
Correspondence; Clippings; Photographs
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition
The papers in this collection were donated by the Forum office.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Correspondence-Incoming, A-C, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming, D-F, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming, G-K, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming, L-R, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming, S-V, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming, W-Z, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing 1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing 1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Outgoing 1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Subscriptions Renewals 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Clower, Jean. Flight into Egypt. The Naturalist. Fanfare. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 4 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Corrigan [Robert W.]. (Forum 3.2, 1959). 26 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Dienstfrey, Harris. A Love Story. Troubles of Town. Straw Man, Wandering Child, Billy the Straw Kid. The Proud and the Profane. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 24 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Doan, Frank. Historicity and the Art Symbol. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 24 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Dozier, Tom. Jung and Jones on U.S. Educational TV. undated. 20 pp. (Box 2)
  - Ekelof, Gunnar. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 4 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Ellenberger, Henri F. The Psychology of Destiny. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 22 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Evans, Richard I. Discussion with Dr. Jung. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 102pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Fiedler, [Leslie A.]. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 20 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth. The Welfare State. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 28 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Gass, [W.H.]. The Case of Obliging Stranger. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 12 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Goeters, H.F. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 11 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Grunbaum, Werner F. The Warren Court and its Critics. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 18 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - [Hungate, Rosa]. (Forum 3.3 1959). 3 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Jensen, James R. FORTUNE and the American Dream. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 19 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Karlen, Arno. Let Us Dedicate These Lines. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 2 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Kaufmann, Walter. Freud. (Forum 3.2, 1959). 14 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - [Kenner, Hugh]. Sweeney and the Voice. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 14 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Kenner, Hugh. The Rational Domain. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 23 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Lyons, Joseph. Magic, Fate, and Delusion. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 31 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Lyons, Joseph. Note Found Inside the Rock. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 26 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - McLuhan, Marshall. (Forum 3.4, 1960).22 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Natanson, Maurice. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 24 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Nemerov, Howard. What Mephisto Meant. Original Thirst. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 2 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Nogee, Joseph. Disarmament as Gamesmenship. (Forum 3.1, 1959). 53 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Parkinson, [C. Northcote]. (Forum 3.2, 1959).14 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Percy, Walker. Science and the Loss of the Creature. (Forum 2.3, 1958). 12 pp. 1958 (Box 2)
  - Percy, Walker. Carnival in Gentilly. (Forum 3.4, 1960).46 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - [Peterson, Roberts]. Poem. The Way My Thoughts Stir. Fiji Marching Band. On. Six Haiku. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 6 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Raines, Charles A. Faulkner and Human Freedom. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 1 p. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Riesman, David. Flight and Search in the New Suburbs. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 1959 (Box 2)
  - Rosenberg, Harold. The Audience as Subject. (Forum 3.3, 1959). 1959. 6 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Toman, Walker, The Do-It-Yourself Living Space. (Forum 3.3, 1959).13 pp. 1959 (Box 2)
  - Tyler, Parker. (Forum 2.3, 1958).10 pp. 1958 (Box 2)
  - Yates, Peter B. (Forum 2.3, 1958). 10 pp. 1958 (Box 2)
  - Yates, Peter B. A Skilled One, A Skilled Job Done, A Long Long Prose and a Long Long Poem, A Portrait of Gertrude Stein. (Forum 3.4, 1960). 21 pp. 1960 (Box 2)
  - Disarmament: An Interpretation. undated. 4 pp. (Box 2)
  - Hegel: Contribution and Calamity. undated. 12 pp. (Box 2)
  - "The man who played …" 24 pp. (Box 2)
  - "The program of the Fifth Annual …" 10 pp. (Box 2)
  - Unidentified corrections. 3 pp. (Box 2)
  - ACPRA Award, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Ads. Sept., Oct., and Nov. 1957 (Box 3)
  - Brando, Marlon. 2 photographs, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Clip art, undated (Box 3)
  - Cullen Building, Ezekiel. 1 photograph, undated. (Box 3)
  - [Forum staff]. 1 photograph, [1958] (Box 3)
  - Forum stationary (Box 3)
  - Grace Borgenicht Gallery, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Harvest, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Magazine Covers, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Magazine Covers, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Magazine Covers, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Martha Jackson Gallery. 8 photographs, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 3)
  - Siporin, Mitchell, ca. 1957 (Box 3)